

IREM B. GÜNDÜZ

PhD Candidate in Computer Science

) igunduz

igunduz.github.io

_igunduz

in ibgunduz

0000-0003-2641-0916

My research centres around the following questions: Which regulatory interactions are involved in changing cell states? What is the role of cell state changes in development systems and disease biology? How can we integrate sparse genomic data to infer disease dynamics? I develop interpretable computational frameworks to perform integrative single-cell multi-omics analysis and, to develop a better understanding of development systems and disease biology.

Education

Oct 2021- Present

Saarland University

Doctor of Philosophy
Computer Science

GPA: 1.0/1.0

Thesis Title: Inferring Regulatory Dynamics of Cell Fate Desicions using Deep Generative

Networks

Supervisor: Prof. Fabian MULLER

Aug 2017-Sep 2021

Marmara Univesity

Bachelor of Engineering Bioengineering (English)

GPA: 3.21/4.00

Thesis Title: Discovery of New Drugs for the Inhibition of N. Meningitidis Computationally

Research Experience

June 2022- Present

Chair of Clinical Bioinformatics

Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Andreas KELLER

Saarland University

As a rotation student, I worked on quantification of alternative splicing events and, transcriptional network breakdown in aging content.

Jan 2022- Present

Integrative Cellular Biology and Bioinformatics Laboratory

Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Fabian MULLER

Saarland University

As a rotation student, I use single-cell bioinformatics to understand epigenomic changes in the content of pathogen explosure .

Bioinformatics and Omics Data Science Group

Supervisor: Dr. Altuna AKALIN

Berlin Institute of Medical System Biology

As a bioinformatics intern, I developed an R package called *deconvR*, to simulate and deconvolute omic profiles. Later, I worked on "Multi-omics alleviates the limitations of panel-sequencing for cancer drug response prediction" manuscript.

Bishop Laboratory

Supervisor: Dr. Alexander J.R. BISHOP, Dr. Daniel MONTEMAYOR

Bioinformatics Research Network

As a project participant, I developed ensembl models to test benefits of using Rloop levels as a predictor for cancer tissue status in clinics.

2021- June 2022

April- Aug 2021

2019- Aug 2021

June - Aug 2019

Computational Biology and Bioinformatics Laboratory

Supervisor: Assoc. Prof. Dr. Pemra OZBEK SARICA

Marmara University

As a student assistant, I worked on computational investigations of biomolecular complexes. I worked on computational drug discovery methodologies.

Neuroscience Laboratory

Supervisor: Assoc. Prof. Dr. Nurcan ORHAN

Aziz Sancar Institute of Experimental Medicine

As an intern, I participitated theoritcal and practical courses on neuroscience and learned how to perform wet-lab techniques such as western blotting, ELISA.

■ Work and Teaching Experience

Sep 2022 - Present

Integrative Cellular Biology and Bioinformatics Laboratory

Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Fabian MULLER

Saarland University

As the teaching assistant of the Single-Cell Bioinformatics course offered in Winter 2022 term at Saarland University, I tutored the assignments and, assisted students.

Aug 2021-Sep 2021

Bioinformatics and Omics Data Science Group

Supervisor: Dr. Altuna AKALIN

Berlin Institute of Medical System Biology

I worked as a teaching assistant in *the CompGen 2021: Hands-on Course on Machine Learning for Genomics*. I prepared the course material, including benchmark machine learning models and assisted the participants for capstone project.

Aug 2020-Oct 2020

VEM Pharmaceuticals

As an intern, I learned how to perform quality tests and, finalize the production of drugs.

Leadership and Volunteer Activities

April 2022-Present

Skill Assessment Team

Bionformatics Research Network (BRN)

As a code reviewer, I assest trainees coding skills in terms of code correctness and, cleanless.

June 2022-Present

Organazition Team

Journal Club in Ageing

As the leader of the club, I keep the club organize to track the up-to-date research in ageing.

June 2022-Present

Community Team

Bionformatics Research Network (BRN)

As the leader of BRN seminar series team, I led and organize series of workshops and presentations to help students to meet leading experts in the field and, track up-to-date research.

Oct 2018-Oct 2020

Journal And Promotion Team

Marmara University Bioengineering Society (BIYOM)

As the head of the team, I led and organize the content for Marmara University Faculty Of Engineering Students Club Magazine (MUFE'M).

Oct 2018–Jan 2019

Organazition Team

IEEE Marmara University Engineering in Medicine&Biology Society (EMBS)

As a team member, I contributed to organization of conferences.

Academic and Professional Honors

- Full Scholarship for Preparatory Phase of Doctoral Studies in Computer Science Saarland University
- TUBITAK 1001 Research Scholarship Marmara University, Department of Bioengineering
- Honor Student Marmara University, Department of Bioengineering

Conferences, Presentations and Relative Engagements

- <u>Single-Cell System Medicine Summer School</u> *Berlin Institute of Medical System Biology*
- <u>Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence (UAI)</u>

Selected Publications and Open-Source Softwares

- **deconvR** (Available in Bioconductor): Simulation and Deconvolution of Omic Profiles
- Baranovskii, A., Gunduz, I. B., Franke, V., Uyar, B., & Akalin, A. (2022). Multi-omics alleviates the limitations of panel-sequencing for cancer drug response prediction. BioRxiv, 2022.06.15.496249. https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.06.15.496249

Courses and Certificates

- Data Science R Basics
- Introduction to Tidyverse
- Intermediate R Programming
- Machine Learning with Caret

- Python for Genomics
- Python Data Structures
- Introduction to Statistics with R
- Unsupervised Learning
- Linux Command Line: Shell Scripting